I guess one thing I and the rest of the staff request is that you, whenever you have a question, you first read the book, and then you reread the assignment, and you maybe reread it again, and then you ask us, because a lot of the questions we're getting are ones where we just say, look at this page of the book, look at this paragraph of the assignment, look at this part of the file that you were given, and so,
So, I mean, there's a lot of stuff and I understand how sometimes it's easy to miss things.
So I'm not saying don't ever ask questions, but just before you ask your questions, try and figure out, have I really sort of come through the resources I have available to see if the answer to my question is, can be found there.
So, anyways, enjoy the lab.
So today is a sort of second part of a two-part lecture lecture on energy.
and integer arithmetic.
Last time we looked at representations about how bit patterns can be interpreted as either unsigned numbers, meaning they range between 0 and 2 to the word size minus 1,
or as two's complement numbers, which is the most common, usual way to represent what are sometimes called sign numbers, ones that can be either negative or positive.
By the way, there are other ways to represent sign numbers out there, but
2's complement is so overwhelmingly the most used system that that's what we concentrate on.
Today, what we'll do is now go beyond the representations of these values to talk about arithmetic operations on them and some of their properties.
And what we'll do in general is talk about the unsigned case, which is in some ways, easier to understand and more intuitive, and then talk
about the two's complement case.
So the basic rule on this is if you take two numbers that range between up to the maximum value
of an unsigned number and you add them, then in principle you might need to get an extra bit to
represent that sum.
If you want to represent the true sum, the sort of integer sum of those two numbers, because
you're doubling it.
And unfortunately, we can't just go out and add more bit.
to your computer indefinitely.
So we just stop it at some point and say, well, whatever
whatever bit happened to be in that sort of next over bit position,
we're just going to drop it and pretend it doesn't exist.
And say that the result of addition is just whatever the
W-bit pattern you get if you only consider the first W bits out of it.
With no warning, no messages, no error or anything.
or anything. This is just, it happens silently.
So for two's complement, this is not such a hard thing to understand.
It can be thought of as just modular arithmetic. Computing modulo the two to the word size.
So I'm going to use some examples, and this time I've got them worked out a little more carefully, so I won't get mixed up as much.
And we'll use a word size of four here. And as I mentioned last time, it
It really helps with this to do the examples with small word sizes to get your
intuition for it rather than trying to write out 32-bit numbers or 64-bit numbers or something
like that.
So if you think about in the unsigned case, a 4-bit number means that it will range between 0 and 2 to
the 4th minus 1 or 15, right?
And so let's just do a few examples of cases where it overflows.
So if you add 13 to 5, first of all, you know, I assume already, that you just add binary numbers the way you learned in school, just doing carries and so forth, except it's all module 2.
So this is 0 carry 1, 0 carry 1, 0 carry 1, 0 carry 1, 0 carry 1, 0 carry 1.
So in principle, to represent the sum, which is, this is 5, so to represent 18, you need 5 bits, not 4.
But we're just going to conveniently drop that number and say that this is actually 2,
which of course, is what 18, module 16 is.
So the unsigned case is really pretty straightforward.
And we can visualize this, and this picture is in the book, too, by saying, if you were representing
on the x and y-axis, what they call u and v, are values between 0 and 15, the range of possible unsigned numbers.
And if we were to add those, we could get a sum that's up to as much as 30, which would in principle require
five bits to represent. But what we'll do is we'll just, by dropping that most significant bit,
what we do is sort of create a cliff that when you roll over from 15,
to 16, instead it drops all the way down to 0.
And that's referred to as an overflow.
And then from there, we'll build up to the maximum value here will be 14,
which is 30 minus 16.
So what we've done is basically, as this picture shows, when we overflow,
we effectively subtract off 2 to the w from the sum
and keep it within the representable range of w bit number.
So that's unsigned.
Two's complement, the first thing I want to convince you of is that two's complement addition looks just like regular addition.
In other words, I can perform subtraction, an addition of subtraction of
by using this two's complement representation for negative numbers.
So let me just show you some examples of that.
of that. So first of all, remember that what range of values, what's the smallest number
that could be represented with a 4-bit, the most negative number, 4-bit, 2's complement number,
minus 8. And the largest, plus 7, thank you.
So let's just do some examples. If we took this number, 1101, as a 2's complement number is minus 3, and we add it to 5.
5 will get what we got before.
And we're not going to, we're going to ignore whatever carry bit it is, and so the result is 2.
And lo and behold, that's what 5 minus 3 is.
So it seems like magic because it is.
And that's why, part of the reason why 2's complement is sort of the most commonly used way
of representing sign numbers, because the same hardware, the same algorithms that are used
that are used for doing addition in works for either unsigned or two complement numbers.
And this works as well, just to show you, just to show you if the overflow goes, if the resulting sum goes the other way.
So if I have minus 3 and minus 5 and plus 3, and I add those together, and I add those together, I'll get 1-5 and plus 3, I'll get 1-5 and plus 3,
I'll get 1-1-0, which is minus 2.
So again, if you use the same patterns for, the same rule for addition,
as you do with unsigned case, you'll get 2's complement arithmetic.
So let's look at a few cases where the 2's complement overflows.
So if we take 3 and minus 6, and we add them together,
add them together, we'll get 1-1-0. We're going to drop off the carry, which is, what, 7?
So we've added two negative numbers and it's become positive, and that's referred to as a negative
overflow. And the reason, of course, is the number minus 9 can't be represented in a 4-bit 2's
complement number, so it overflowed.
You'll notice that the plus 7, of course, differs from minus 9 by 16, and that's not an accident.
And then going the other direction, if we had two large positive numbers, so if we had 7 and 5, we'll get minus 6.
So this was 7 plus 5 is minus 4.
And so this is referred to as positive overflow.
We've taken 2.
positive numbers and added them together and gotten a negative result.
And you could see this, by the way, if you think about this addition, we took 7 and 5 would be 12.
And this is the bit level representation of 12.
It's just that because this is now the sign bit, we think of that as minus 4, not positive 12.
And so that's the idea of 2's complement overflow.
And you can see there's two different cases here.
One is where the number that the sum was, if we looked at the true sum, the number that you'd get, for example, 12, is too big to represent.
And so when we think of that as a two's complement number, it becomes now a negative number.
So that's positive overflow.
Similarly, if we have two negative numbers and we add them together so that the sum is too small,
two negative to represent, then those become positive numbers.
That's negative overflow.
And you can see that in this picture, the same idea as before, except there's three regions.
This is the, and by the way, now you'll see our numbers range between minus 8 and positive 7, and the sum, two's common
also range between minus 8 and positive 7.
But there's these three.
regions. One is the where everything's fine. It's within the
the representable range. The other is where the sum was so far toward the
negative side that it becomes positive or where it's so high on the
the positive side that it becomes negative. And so part of data lab, you'll
you'll learn to understand these quite in quite precisely. But
That's the idea, and it's a little bit counterintuitive to say, you know, somehow I can accept the idea that modular arithmetic for unsigned numbers,
there's some sort of mathematical beauty to modular arithmetic.
And this just looks like kind of useless, right, from a operational characteristic.
But it's the way it is, and we're stuck with it.
And multiplication is basically the same idea.
In fact, all the operations are basically the same idea,
that if you can't represent it within the word size,
you just take the lower W bits.
So all this complicated notation here is just a way of saying,
in principle, if you take two W-bit numbers and multiply them together,
you may need, the result may require as much as two times W-w-bits
to represent before addition it's w plus one multiplication you actually have to double
because you're potentially squaring the largest number and so again we don't want to
just keep doubling our word size over and over again we'll run out of bits very
quickly that way and so we just truncated it at w bits and for the unsigned case it's
again modular arithmetic it's something
that you can kind of understand and believe.
But for, and so again, let's just do a few examples.
And I won't try and work out multiplying in binary is like multiplying in binary is like multiplying in decimal.
You do a big table and it takes a long time.
So I won't try to do that.
But let me just show a few examples.
So if I multiply three times five is, of course, equal to 15,
And in an unsigned number, I can represent that, right?
So that's okay.
But if I multiply five times five, then that would have a representation,
if I were to think about it as possibly as many as eight bits,
it would have a representation with an extra bit.
And I'm going to throw this part away, and so I'd call that nine,
which, of course, is equal to 25 mod 16.
And so that's the general idea of it,
is regardless of whatever is in this upper part of the product,
I'm just going to discard that and only look at the lower one.
And life gets a little more interesting with the two's complement case.
So let's look at what that does.
And the answer is, even a little bit stranger,
and that you not only trunk, throw away whatever high order bits happen to be there,
but whatever bit gets left and that you not only trunk,
gets left in this position will determine whether it's a positive or a negative result,
even though with completely irrespective of the signs of the original two operands.
So that can make you go all over the place.
So if we had 5 times 4 or 20, that would be represented in this 8-bit form like so,
we'd just call that 4, right, because we're throwing this away.
But if we did 5 times 5, as we saw before, that's represented like this, and that's now
becomes, so we're throwing away this, and this becomes our sine bit, so the result is minus
8 plus 1 or minus 7.
So you see this is similar to an example we showed at the beginning of the first lecture that you can
have two positive numbers.
and multiply them and get a negative result.
And because of the sort of quirks of this overflow.
Question there.
Oh, I'm just taking 25 and writing it in binary.
Yeah, if you want to.
You know, you start with the two numbers.
I'm not going to do.
Well, actually, this one's an easy one.
There's a trick for this.
If you want to multiply a number by a power of two,
we're going to show that later.
You just shift it left by two positions.
two positions.
So that one's an easy one.
Otherwise, you have to write out the table and sum all the results and all that stuff.
I prefer to let computers do that.
And again, the two's complement stuff, one interesting feature is that it works for negative numbers, too,
if you do this trick of throwing away the high order bits.
And you'll have overflow cases like before because you're throwing away information.
But the lower bits, if the number is representable, you'll get the right result.
So let me just demonstrate to that to you.
So this is minus 3.
But you remember that this is equivalent to 13 as an unsigned number.
And this is minus 2, which is equivalent to 14 as an unsigned number. And this is minus 2.
which is equivalent to 14 as an unsigned number.
So now if we multiply 13 times 14, you get 182,
and that has a hex representation of b6.
And so just looking at the low order 4 bits,
our 110, is 6, and indeed, that's negative 3 times minus 2 is 6.
So the point being, uh, 0 110 is 6.
and I'm waving my hands here because I don't want to go through all the details.
But 2 complement multiplication also gives you, if you can do it using the exact same rules,
and as you do for unsigned multiplication, the exact same hardware.
I should mention that there are instructions in the computer in ways that you can get
the upper word of a multiplication, too.
And those, the bit patterns are different, depending on
whether it's treated as a two's complement number versus unsigned.
So there's typically different instructions for doing that computation.
But 99% of the time or more, you just are looking at this lower part of the product.
And that's the same, whether it's a two's complement or an unsigned.
And it handles negative numbers positive, but it has these overflow characteristics.
So as I was talking about, there's a trick we can do for multiple
by a power of 2, which is just to shift the number to the left.
And you'll often see that when you have in your code, I want to multiply some number by 4.
You'll write in your C code.
If you look at the assembly code, you'll see that what the compiler generated is just says,
oh, just shift it left by 2.
So in general, and you can see why this is true, by the way, if you think of the number as the sum of the bits,
where x is the ith bit and x is the number it represents.
If I want to, if I shift everything left by 2, what I'm effectively doing is increasing their weight by
that number of positions.
So let's just shift by 1.
If I shift everything to the left by 1, which we write like this and C,
two left, two less symbols.
It's like taking that sum.
but now weighting the bits by 2 to the i plus 1,
by one, by one more.
And of course, that's equal to twice what the original sum was.
And so we double the number.
And that works also, even if you shift things, so that you lose some bits, right?
They shift off to the left.
All you're doing is the way multiplication works anyhow
of truncating to a W-bit product.
So you'll see that.
this, as I mentioned quite often in compiled code and machine level code that they're doing shifts
where you might expect them to be doing multiplications.
And the reason for that is an optimization is,
historically, the multiplication instruction took a lot longer than a shift instruction.
Say, one clock cycle to do a shift,
and it used to be like 11, 12, 30 clock cycles to do a multiplication.
Nowadays, like I'm going to do a shift.
On the computers, we use the shark machines,
it only takes three clock cycles to do multiplication
because they added a lot of hardware to do that.
But three clock cycles is still more time than one.
And so when you can get away with a shift, it's generally a better idea.
And the compiler has its own kind of judgment calls on when is it more
efficient to substitute one operation for another.
Did we, uh, did I lose ground here?
Okay.
So, um, the idea then if we want to, uh, multiply something by 2 to the k, we just shift it left by k bits.
Um, it turns out that the same almost works for dividing by 2 as well, that if you want
to divide something by a power of 2, you can shift it right by, uh, in the same general idea.
The only thing that becomes a little bit of 2, uh, you can shift it right by this in the same general idea.
The only thing that
becomes a little bit quirky is, well, what if the number you have is not actually
divisible by that power of two?
So, uh, for example, if we had the number 01, um, I'm going to use this.
So that's six.
So if we shift it right by 1, we'll get 00,0,0, 1, thank you, which is 3, and that's 6, and that's 6 divided by 2
is 3. If we shift that again, we'll get 1.
But of course, you know that 3 halves are 1.5, the rule on integer division is you round it down,
round it towards 0, and so that goes to 1.
So this is what the unsigned case works fine.
The sign case, which I don't have a slide for, is a slide for, is a little
bit less pretty. Well, first of all, you notice if it's a positive number, the shifting
right is going to be the right thing, just as it is for unsigned. But let's take a number
that is negative. So this is minus six, right? Now, here's where, remember, remember I told
you in the previous lecture, there's two ways to do shifting. There's
logical shifting where you fill in with zeros and arithmetic shifting where you fill in with ones.
And guess where arithmetic shifting comes in?
This is it.
When you want to preserve the sign of a number while you're dividing it by powers of two,
you want arithmetic shifts.
So if we shift this by one, we'll keep that sign bit and then copy the other ones over.
right? So we just preserved this bit here and copied the other ones over.
And this is minus 3. And so that's good. But now if we shift again,
arithmetically, we'll get what? Nice 2. I can see you guys need to know how to negate numbers, right?
You don't know that? So I'll show you in a second. So here is a little bit problematic that we shifted. We want to divide by 2.
but the rule should be the same, that you should round toward zero.
And what this is doing is it's rounding toward minus infinity.
It's rounding toward a more negative number than the true thing.
And so there's a little, a cute little trick that says,
before you shift, before you divide by a power of two,
before you do the shift, you should add a bias,
which in this case would just be one.
And I'll tell you where the shift.
that comes from. And so if we add those numbers together, we'll get
1-1-1-0, right? And now when we do the shift on that,
we'll get 1-1-1-1, and that's minus 1. So there's a trick,
and again, you'll see the compiler doing this, where you have in your code,
divide by 16, and it will add a bias, and then it will do a right shift instead
of calling division. And by the way, division really, really is slow.
even on a modern computer like what you have, the shark machines.
It takes 30 plus clock cycles.
So anytime the compiler can avoid, figure out a trick that does it with shifting
and tweaking things around it will.
So I realize I should tell you there's a couple ways you can negate a number
that are handy to know if you ever have to do it in your head or on paper.
And the standard way is what you can.
It's called complement and increment.
So this is, how do I go from x to minus x?
So if I have a number and I want to negate it,
whether it's currently a negative number or it's a positive number,
or it's a positive number.
The same trick works.
What I'll do is complement it, meaning I'll flip all of the bits.
And then I'll add one to that and do the regular sum.
And so this is six, this is minus six.
So if you ever have to do it by hand, that's the way to do it.
complement and it goes the other way.
You'll see if I complement this and I increment it, I'll get back to my previous number.
So that's a trick that is pretty much only useful when you do things on the blackboard,
or when you have to solve a problem in data lab.
So anyways, this idea of doing a, shifting to the right to do power of two division,
is actually that's the whole justification for arithmetic shifting in the first place.
Which by the way, in C, there's no fixed requirement for how shifting works in C for
sign numbers. For unsigned, it has to be a logical shift. Sign numbers, the C standard says
there's no fixed definition. The reality is on our machines, most machines, just
about every machine out there, when it's a two's complement.
complement number, when it's a negative, when it's a sign number, it's two's complement.
And when you do a shift, it will be an arithmetic shift.
So getting back to then summarizing this integer arithmetic, you see that, first of all, whether
it's signed or unsigned, the addition or multiplication operations are the same, whether
it's a unsigned number or two's complement.
And it works.
the negative stuff works out as long as you don't have an overflow.
And you can end up with an overflow, only one type of overflow for unsigned and two types for sign numbers.
But it's not like they just overflow and generate random numbers.
There's some pattern to what result, what they are, and how they can be interpreted.
So I talked about this a little bit last time and gave this.
examples similar to this,
but let me go over it a little bit more.
One thing you might think of,
wow, if this unsigned and signed stuff gets so murky,
and we saw some funny examples last time,
maybe we should just banished unsigned numbers from the universe
and only allow two's complement.
And that's exactly the rule that was adopted,
for example, in Java.
They said, oh, this is too weird.
Let's just say every number is two's complement.
The only trick they did was they put in a triple right shift means logical shift.
This is Java.
This is not C.
Whereas the double is arithmetic.
So, because they realize there's a lot of cute little times when you want to play tricks with things.
And you need that logical right shift.
So that's actually one approach.
Or other more modern languages in C are saying,
it's okay to have signed and unsigned, but we don't want
them sort of mysteriously being cast back and forth
in ways that the programmer might not recognize.
And so you have to explicitly do a cast rather than implicitly.
And I think that's the better approach.
But C, as I mentioned, does this implicit casting.
And so as we saw for last time, what happens with this
program when you run it to count down through an array.
Do you remember?
Well, is I, if it's unsigned, what will happen with this test?
It always succeeds.
So the thing will be in an infinite loop.
Actually, what will happen is it will try to access,
I will go down to zero and then it will wrap around
to become the largest possible unsigned number,
which is probably way out of bounds and it will give a memory error.
memory error, but it won't do what's supposed to be.
And as I mentioned before, these things, there's a lot of sneaky ways this problem can show up in ways you might
never think of.
So for example, the operator size of is defined to say how big a particular data type is.
It's a very useful operator, but its return value is what's called a size underscore T, which is a
which is defined to be a long unsigned number.
And so if we just throw in a constant like this, then this subtraction, we have a sign,
I is now int, but size of is unsigned, and so it will cast that to be unsigned implicitly.
And when you compare it to zero, you'll have the same problem as before.
So just to show you that these things can sneak in in very,
in very tricky ways.
So one way to do that then is just don't use unsigned.
Like, and make sure if this is a possible unsigned number, you cast it to sign.
You make sure that this is recognized it signed.
But there's another way that actually, at least there's a fellow over in the Software Engineering Institute
Institute named Robert Seacord, who has written the books that are considered the
the gold standard for how to write secure code.
He works for this organization called the Computer Emergency Response Team,
which is out there tracking down bad things going on in computer security.
And one of the things he and others have done is to try and come up with standards so that
that people who write programs will, you know, avoid some of the pitfalls that
make their programs vulnerable to security flaws, to attack.
And so his recommended technique is when I first saw this, it was so counterintuitive
to me, it hardly made sense, right? So you start, and again, this is all unsigned
arithmetic. So I'm starting to count down, and my test is when I is less than count down,
So here's the thing.
I started off smaller than count, and it's only being decremented.
So when would this test ever fail?
Hmm?
When it overflows, when it wraps around, right?
When I goes from zero and counts down to what would now be U max,
this test will fail, which is exactly when you want it to stop.
And his observation is, in C, with sign numbers, there's no guarantee
on what happens with overflowing.
As I said, most people just assume it's going to be two's compliment,
but if you really want to be careful, you shouldn't assume anything outside of the C standard.
And if you're trying to write secure code, it's probably a good idea to be cautious, be conservative.
On the other hand, the C standard guarantees it that unsigned arithmetic will be modular arithmetic.
So it guarantees that if you subtract one from zero, you'll get the line.
largest number that could be represented.
So it will be okay.
And in fact, he recommends instead of using unsigned, which is on our machine's just a 32-bit value,
that you call it a size T, which is a 64-bit value, and so, and write your code the way that I showed you.
So I've actually started doing this, and once you kind of get used to it, it's an okay way to write code.
but it's very strange looking initially.
One thing I'll point out is, what would happen if count were a sign number, an int, and it were
you were, and it was less than zero, what would happen here?
So I less than count, what would happen?
Hmm?
Right.
And so it would become a very large positive number, and this test would almost certainly
succeed. So you have the same, this code doesn't avoid the pitfall.
It just shifts it to saying, you better make sure you don't, you know, test for this case beforehand
before you get into it.
So I think part of it is the observation that, Nan, if you want to be careful and write code
that is guaranteed correct, no matter what implementation goes on, as long as it's within the C standard,
It's pretty tricky business.
A question up there.
Yes.
Which is unfortunate.
Right? So yes, that's exactly the rule.
That it's implicitly, silently.
The C compiler doesn't give any warnings.
You'll never know.
It casts it to unsigned.
And as these examples show,
when you stare at that code and you think about it,
it's really easy to have bugs that you just,
you can look at it a thousand times and not realize that it's
realize that it's a bug.
It's a very, and there's examples, there's examples in the book of
security flaws in sort of very important library software due to this problem exactly.
So part of the reason we teach in the course is just so you appreciate that this is
is a quirk in this and see that, again, 99% of the time you'll never even, it won't bother you at all,
there will be some oddball cases that you can get in trouble with.
So the other place that you'll find unsigned arithmetic, unsigned representation useful is first of all,
when you're doing modular arithmetic, which is, for example,
the way most encryption algorithms work, or when you're using the bits not to represent numbers,
but to represent sets, the way I described it before, then
you don't want to, it's easiest to just think of that as unsigned numbers.
Okay, so the final thing to talk about today is
some of the low-level representations of numbers within memory.
And the main point is when you are running a program on a computer,
from the programming perspective,
even as an assembly level programmer, not just as a C programmer,
In your mind, the memory is just this big array of bytes that's numbered from zero up to some maximum number.
So for example, in the machines we're using, the 64-bit machines, an address is represented in 64 bits, but in fact, the maximum address you're allowed to use in current machines, is 47 bits.
And 2 to the 47th is still a pretty big number.
So that's more memory than anyone's able to buy right now anyhow.
And so that's a reasonable restriction.
But the point is that logically,
your program thinks that it has an array of that many bytes.
Let's try and figure out how big 2 to the 47th is.
Anyone know it off the top of their head?
So there's a trick if you want to get an approximate
idea, which is to say that 2 to the 10th, which is 100, 1024, is approximately equal to 10 to the 3rd.
You say, oh, well, that's really helpful. What it means is that 10 bits worth of number is about the same as 3 decimal digits.
All right? So, so, for example, for example, so for example, two to the 20th,
is around 10 to the 6th.
2 to the 30th, it's around 10 to the 9th.
2 to the 40th, it's around 10 to the 12th,
it's around 10 to the 12th.
And so that would tell you that 2 to the 48th,
47th is around 128 times 10 to the 12th, which is 128
128 terabytes, right?
Terra, 10 to the 12th.
So if you just want to say, you know, get
a quick figure for, and of course, these are approximations, but if you just want to get a quick handle on how big a number, you know, what range of values can I represent with so many bits of it, this is a really easy trick to do that.
So the point is, um, a hundred twenty-eight terabytes is a lot. You can buy disk drives, a couple of disk drives will do that for you, but you couldn't buy enough DRAM on a normal budget to
to get that kind of memory.
So that's the current range of values.
But logically,
when you run a program,
it thinks that it has that possible range.
Now, it doesn't really.
And in fact, what happens is that the operating system
only allows certain regions within that memory to be
referenced.
And other regions, if you try to access them,
it will create a, it will signal and error,
what they call a segmentation fault.
But logically at least, it's as if you
you have this big array of bytes.
Now, in reality, and we'll go into this when we talk about how the memory
system works in virtual memory, there's this very complex combination of hardware and software that
gives the program this image of a very large, what you call flat space, just a big array of
bytes, when in reality it's shuffling between different regions of your memory and even between your
memory and your disk drive on your computer to make it implement this particular
idea that you have this big array of bytes.
And that's all handled, as I said, by the operating system, by the computer hardware,
and it's largely invisible even to the machine-level programmer, even people writing assembly code.
You'll often hear the term word size, and it can get very confusing nowadays because
there's no really fixed idea of what a word size is.
But roughly speaking, the word size should be whatever the largest number is that,
or the range that sort of signifies how big a pointer is in this language.
Or hardware-wise, the largest sort of chunk of hardware for which there's standard support for storing it,
it for arithmetic operations and so forth.
So when we say it's a 64-bit machine,
what we mean is that it regular and routinely
manipulate 64-bit values on arithmetic operations,
and also it has pointers or the values of addresses are 64-bit
even if, for right now, only 47 of those bits are usable.
It's still considered a 64-bit machine.
One thing that's strange is in one of the features
of machines such as we have is that if I compile a program
using a GCC is the standard compiler,
I can specify either I want it to be 64-bit code
or 32-bit code as a flag,
and it will actually generate two different kinds of object code as a flag.
code as a result. And we'll talk in a little about these later.
But for right now, the point is the hardware itself doesn't necessarily define what the word size is.
It's a combination of the hardware and the compiler that determines what is the word size
being used in this particular program.
And that code can be run on the point is a 64-bit machine,
such as we have, and most machines are nowadays, can insert of a, uh,
and sort of a backward compatibility style also execute 32-bit code.
And as we also saw, one of the other features is even though it's a 64-bit word size, the data type
int without any other qualifiers to it, is just 32-bit.
So there's sort of this mixture of how big things are.
So when people just say word or word size, unless they give a precise definition that's not a
very meaningful term. And we'll sort of throw it around when we mean sort of a generic
chunk of bits without trying to assume that it has a particular number of bits to it.
Yes, so one of the things is if we ever get to 64-bit words, it will be 16 petabytes,
18 petabytes depending on how you define. When you, those numbers get big, the the error due
to this approximation gets more significant.
but something times 10 to the 15th bytes.
But right now, we can only get to 128 times 10 to the 12th.
So anyways, the idea that the memory itself is a series of bytes, but we can group those into blocks of words of different word sizes.
And the way we do that is usually by assuming that the address of the word sizes, the way we do that is usually by usually by assuming that the address of
the word is the lowest valued address in it.
And we also will generally try to align these so that, for example, a 32-bit word would be aligned
so its first byte, its lowest byte has all zeros in the first, in the first five-bit
positions, right?
No, 32, 4, I'm sorry, the lowest 2 bytes.
Right.
So as this example shows, their addresses 0, 4, 8, and 12.
They should have really written this in hex instead at C.
I guess these are all in decimal anyhow.
So yeah, these are decimal numbers.
So 0, 4, 8, 12.
So you see these are in multiples of 4-bit boundaries.
And similarly, the 64-bit were
are on multiples of eight.
And those are known as aligned words, and we'll generally,
we'll see that the compiler works pretty hard to keep things aligned
because the hardware runs more efficiently that way.
But the main point is that we can just take as many bytes as we want
and collect them together and call it a word for whatever word size we need.
And as we, I think we saw a variant to this table before,
but this is the machines we'll be working on that the stings.
The standard int is still only 32 bits, but if we qualify something as being long, then it will be 64 bits.
And we'll tend to do that.
There's two different floating point representations that we'll talk about.
And then the main feature of a 64-bit machine is it has an 8 byte or 64-bit pointer as compared to a 32.
Now there's one other kind of detail that says, okay, so
So if a word has multiple bites in it, what order should those bites be?
Should it be?
And there's two basic ways this could go.
One is that you put the bites in what's known as Little Indian order,
meaning that the first bite in the word is the least significant bite,
and then the next, and then the next,
and the final bite in the word is the most significant.
Or you can flip that around.
And those are called Little Indian and Big
Indian is the sort of terms for that which comes from
an English book called Gulliver's Travels, which didn't anticipate
computers at all.
But it's an interesting story of how that comes about.
So out there in the world, you'll find both types of machines,
big Indian and little Indian machines.
It turns out that increasingly it's getting hard to find big Indian machines.
So little Indian, all of x86 is little Indian.
And it turns out arm processors, like what you have in almost every cell phone here, is an arm processor.
And the hardware in those can actually be configured to run either way, Big Indian or Little Indian.
But when you're running it on any of the standard operating systems that run on arm processors,
then it's running little Indian.
running little Indian.
So there used to be a brand called Sun, Microsystems, and they were fairly common on campus.
And then back at the Macintosh, before they were x86 processors, they ran one called the PowerPC.
And that was a big Indian machine.
But those are long in the distant past.
The Internet's about the only place out there when you send packets over the internet and you want to send packets over the internet
and you want to send, you know, 32-bit words.
They're actually sent in big Indian order.
And so at the network interface, you have to translate between those two.
So again, just to illustrate what I mean by this, is think of a byte value, four-byte value, like this.
And remember that the way we write numbers is we put the most significant to the left and the least significant to the right.
And so now with Big Indian is sort of the intuitive one from that perspective
in that the bites, if you write the words in memory from the smallest address up to the highest,
the Big Indian will sort of map to what you see.
Whereas the little Indian will look confusing,
that you say 01, 2, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
Because 6, 6, is actually the least,
significant bite here and so that comes first in little Indian order.
And so it used to be people would get in passionate arguments about this.
That's sort of in the distant past. But, and people saying, you know, and the main feature
in sort of argument of big Indianness is this feature here, that when you look at it,
it's easier to write down. But computers don't really care. They're happy.
either way. And so they just want one convention or another. And like I said,
some hardwares can actually be by a sort of flag to flip it from being Big Indian to
little Indian. But the reality is most of the machines will encounter, you'll
encounter are Little Indian machines nowadays. But just to give you an example, here's
some results that I got from actual machines. There used to be some machines around.
So back in the old days, I could run this. I don't even know where to
to get a big Indian machine anymore.
So these are sort of legacy results.
But you'll see that the main feature is between a little Indian and a big Indian machine.
When you have an integer, the bytes get flipped around.
So that the least significant bite comes first in a little Indian machine and last in a big Indian machine.
And that's true with negative numbers as well.
that you'll get the sign bits first in a big Indian machine.
Along, you'll see that the only difference between a 32-bit machine and a 64-bit machine is you have more zeros or more ones,
depending whether it's a positive or a negative number.
And again, a Sun, and if I had access to a 64-bit machine, Sun is now manufactured by a
company called Oracle. So in principle, I could go get one of these machines
and run this experiment, but it's really not a very interesting experiment, so I won't
bother. So in principle, I could try it on a 64-bit
bit Oracle machine and show you something different. So one thing that's kind of a useful
tool, and the book goes through some examples of this, is a little program that will
take a series of bytes, starting at some position start, and do it for however
many bytes you request.
And just print out in hex format the two hex digits that represent that byte value.
And here, this term pointer, I'm using an unsigned care as a pointer type, a sort of generic pointer type.
And so again, if I run this on a x86 machine,
I'm also, by the way, printing out the actual address that this character is stored at, too.
And so you'll see that there's these addresses with a lot of 7Fs.
What that means is it's in the upper end of this 47-bit address space.
If you work it through, there's 7.
7 is 3-1s and then there's enough hex digits here to correspond to
so there's 11 hex digits beyond the 7.
And you'll see that these addresses are at successive bytes, B-C, B-D, B-D, B-E, B-F, and the values are 6D, 3B-0-0-0.
This is the least significant byte, and these are the successive bytes.
And similarly, I can use this to examine pointers of various sorts, and I can examine
different values and just get their low-level byte representations.
And so I did this back when I could get to a Sun machine.
It had one way of representing a pointer.
And the main point is, even across machines, whether it's byte ordering or whatever,
you'll get different values for pointers.
There's no guarantee that when you load a machine,
computer program into one machine and run it, then it will use the same addresses
as that same programming running on a different machine, even if actually they're
identical hardware and operating system. There can be variation. Because pointers aren't,
you can't directly copy a pointer from one machine to another. On, on, one thing
about also is regardless of byte ordering, the ordering of, of characters is that
the same. And so a string in C is always represented by a series of bytes where the final
byte is zero, called null terminated, and the individual bytes correspond to the character codes for that number.
And these character codes are just sometimes called ASCY format, which is a little bit
old-fashioned, by the way. There's more modern character codes that can represent
non-English alphabets. But the C standard is still back in the days of only supporting the ASC format.
Question. Uh-huh? Yes. So this should have been, well, no, this is good. So I'm casting, I want to show the
the 4 byte size of int, because this is an int I'm representing. The pointer, let's see, the code,
where it's printing the pointer, all this notation.
Percent P is the directive to say, print out a pointer.
Right?
And percent X is the directive to print out a hex representation.
So it's printing out both the address, the starting position of that particular byte,
and the value of that byte as two different things.
Does that answer your question?
Yes.
Ah.
But remember.
The number of show bytes is being given a pointer and a length.
And so what this is, and what it's saying is, starting at that address, print out the next series of bytes for me,
how many bytes I ask for.
And in this case, I'm, I'm creating a pointer to this integer, but I want to show the, the bytes in
that integer, the four bytes that make up that integer.
And that's why I'm giving it the number of the number of.
four here instead of eight is it yes it will be and that's fine
because in this code it's I'm using the percent P directive to designate how to
print out the pointer and that will print it as many bytes as it takes for that
particular machine that it's running on so percent P is actually a very handy
directive if you have to print an address is like for debugging purposes or
something because it will automatically adapt to whatever machine it's running
on.
Question?
Well, I've defined it to be an unsigned care here.
So type def is a way to introduce a name for some data type, right?
And so I've just declared a pointer, quote, pointer, to refer to an unsigned care.
If you did avoid star, it would not be happy with this reference here, right?
You can't reference, avoid star is just a way to pass around a generic pointer, but you can't actually reference that element.
So what I'm basically doing is saying this reference is treat it like an array.
Treat my series of bytes as an array and print out each of the bytes in that array.
And so here where I'm, A is a number, and I'm a number.
taking the address of that integer and casting it to be an unsigned care star.
So sort of a generic, slightly generic pointer, but not quite as generic as generic as a void star.
And then printing it out.
Those are good questions, by the way.
Okay, so the point being that strings are just strings, and that's the same from one machine to the next.
Okay, let's finish up today with some puzzles.
And these have this annoying.
way of showing up on exams. So it's worth being able to do these kind of things.
And you'll also notice I cleverly did not include the answers in the slides. So you can't, you
can't just peek ahead and figure out what the answers are. So let's just go through them, but
I actually worked them out to make sure I had the answers right. So if X, and
basically these are sort of statements that you want to say these are either always
true and maybe there's some logic behind why it's always true.
true or it's possibly false and you want to have to give some example that
would make that false. So let's go through these as many as we have time for and see
where we get to. So if I take x and I double it, multiply it by 2, if x were
negative, am I guaranteed that 2x will be negative? No. So by the way, one
general way to find counter examples is to try tmin.
It's a really good one.
And that works here, right?
If I take T-Men, which is 1 and a bunch of zeros, I double it,
it's like shifting it but left, and it will become what?
Zero.
Right.
And so again, assume that x is at any negative number and ux is its unsigned,
I'm sorry, any two's complement number,
and ux is what happens if I cast it to be unsigned.
So is ux always greater than equal to zero?
Yeah.
It's slightly more obscure.
If I take X and I mask off 7, you remember, is the bit pattern 1-1-1-1.
So if I mask off all but the lowest 3 bits, and I find that those are all ones, I'm already giving
you the answer here, and then I shift it left by 30 positions, what can I say about the result?
So I know the X must finish with 3 ones, right?
And I shift that by 30, and these will be the only two bits that are left after the shifting,
and they will be in the most significant position.
So what can I say about that number?
It's negative.
So this is a true statement.
Rather obscure, but it is true.
Is ux greater than minus 1?
It's almost true, right?
The one counter example would be what?
0.
Well, actually, no, you're right.
There's a lot of examples.
It's hardly ever true.
It's almost always false.
I was wrong.
The only thing that would make it true would be,
actually it's never true.
Okay.
So it's never true.
If x is greater than y is minus x less than minus y.
No.
So by the way, one thing we didn't really cover is
what is the negative of tmin?
And to see that we can use our
complement and increment trick. So when you complement and increment T min, you get T min.
And that's why it's such a great counter-example. So in particular, if Y is T-min and X is something
else, then that left-hand part will be true, but the right-hand part will not be true.
Okay, x times x greater than or equal to zero. We've seen examples of that.
examples of that being false.
If x is, this is kind of silly, if x is greater than 0 and y is greater than 0,
is x plus y greater than 0, no.
If x is greater than or equal to 0 is minus x less than or equal to 0.
Gotcha.
You're right, it's true, right?
Because that, but let's take its counterpart,
if x is less than or equal to 0 is minus x greater than equal to 0,
tmin, right?
So.
Right, the point being that the largest,
any positive number can be represented as negative,
but there's one negative number that can't be represented as positive.
And so that asymmetry is why you get different answers to these.
If I take x and I look at minus x and I shift them to the right by 31,
am I going to get all ones?
This is a really weird statement.
So it actually kind of works, right?
right?
If I take all zeros and I subtract 1, I'll get minus 1, and I order them?
That works.
So what's wrong with this?
What's that?
Oh, but if I shift this to the right 31 places,
it's going to shift arithmatically.
What's that?
Oh, I see.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I already jumped ahead to a different puzzle.
X and minus x, and I'm...
So you're right, actually.
If the two numbers.
numbers are zero and I or those I get zero but you'll figure out you'll notice
if it's anything non-zero actually this will be true and that's an interesting feature.
So there's a couple other puzzles and I'll let you solve those on your own.
We're all set for today.